Fable 5 came back online globally on
July 1st with a few provisos. This feels
like the first time a frontier model has
a standing duty to the US government.
This is probably close to the best
scenario we could have hoped for.
>> Sam has been talking to Trump Lutnik
Bessant and Bernie Sanders about a 5%
equity stake in open AI. That 5% stake
would be worth about 42.6 billion. The
idea that the government is going to set
up some intelligent sovereign wealth
equity thing is absolutely insane. The
next president will immediately sell it
all, turn it into cash, and then [music]
use it to buy votes in the next
election. Yesterday, Anthropic just
published a paper titled a [music]
global workspace in language models,
claiming they found something inside
Claude that looks a lot like the
machinery of consciousness. If we can
understand the innermost thoughts of
these models, then there's a chance to
actually shape them.
>> This is so exciting, Peter. I think I
can see the end game. The endame looks
like this.
>> Now, that's a moonshot, ladies and
gentlemen.
>> So, See, where are you today? You're not
at home. Uh I'm in Mayorca in Spain at a
retreat hosted by the Festival of
Consciousness
>> which is a conference we just got. It's
a conference coming up this weekend in
Barcelona. We helped curate this and
help put this together in the original
years. Several thousand people show up
at the Barcelona Convention Center for
kind of an experiential uh uh
understanding of consciousness.
>> Well, we're going to talk about AI and
consciousness today. So that's good. I'm
>> We are indeed.
>> I am the uh pot calling the kettle
black. I'm in Germany at this moment and
off to
>> off to Greece tomorrow. Yeah. Just got
back from Calgary where my kids are now
doing a month-long uh sort of uh
learning responsibility and hard work on
a ranch. Let's put it that way.
>> That's awesome.
>> Wow. What kind of ranch? It's like
>> Yeah. It's cattle and horses. They're
going to be mending fences. They're
going to be doing all kinds of things
from a dear friend whose name I don't
want to mention but cuz he likes his
privacy. But yeah, amazing. Uh, all
right. Uh,
>> Peter, did did I hear correctly? You're
teaching them an abundance mentality
through farmwork. [laughter]
>> I'm teaching them uh what it used to be
like before the robots arrived.
>> Abundance.
>> Abundance is earned.
>> Yeah, good deal. I I appreciate that
concept. Um, I am excited about today's
episode without any question whatsoever.
Uh there is a lot uh and it's kind of
insane. So let me kick it off here.
Welcome everybody to Moonshots, your
number one podcast on all things AI and
exponential. Your front row seat to the
singularity here with my incredible
moonshot mates AWG, our in-house AGI.
I'm elevating soon.
>> I've been down I've been downgraded from
ASI to AGI. Thanks.
>> I'm going to I'm going to work your way
up ASI. You know where do you go from
being an ASI? I can't cut a break.
>> Oh my god. Dave London, our emperor of
AI investing and Sim Ismael, our globe
trotder and master of the organizational
singularity. I'm Peter D. Mandis, your
host and your abundance amplifier. This
past week has been utterly insane. It
feels like a decade compressed into uh
into seven days, and I can't wait to get
into it. Today we're going to cover nine
stories including Anthropic's Fable 5
model coming back online and the
imminent release of GPT 5.6.
Has it been up? Is it up yet, Alex?
>> Not as of the last time I checked.
>> Okay. Well, we'll find out if it pops up
during this. Anyway, uh we'll discuss
evidence of something inside Claude that
looks a lot like the machinery of
conscious thought. Next, we'll dive into
OpenAI's offer of equity to the US
government, Sam Alman's proposal for
global regulation. Fascinating
conversation. Finally, we're going to
get a review of new jobs data that
counters the prevailing narrative that
AI is inducing job loss. And we'll
discuss the acceleration of the
innermost loop. Uh, an incredible story
of AI building better AI chips to build
better AI. As always, our mission here
on Moonshots is to keep you up to speed,
help you understand what's going on,
what the impact is to you, your
business, your life, your family, and
most importantly, to keep you optimistic
about the future. All right, gentlemen.
Uh, let's dive in. Uh, our first story,
the return of Fable 5. Uh, it's a
continuing saga, the triumphant global
return. Uh, if you haven't been watching
this story, let me give you a quick
recap. Let's rewind back to June 9th.
Enthropic released its mega models,
Mythos 5 and Fable 5. You can think of
Fable as a guardrail version of Mythos
5. Then 3 days later, after everybody
got addicted to this incredible
capability, the White House came out
with an export control action against
Anthropic, saying you can't make it
available to foreign nationals. And of
course, Anthropic has no idea who's a
foreign national. There's no KYC, at
least not yet. Uh even they shut it down
for everybody cuz they couldn't even
enable their own employees to have it
because Anthropic um was shut down. The
question is why? It turns out that a
researcher at Amazon had found out how
to break the guard rails. Uh what
happened next was fascinating. uh there
was a a week of frenzied research by uh
anthropic by Amazon by the US government
investigating what happened and what
they found out was an additional fable 5
opus 4.8 8 GPT 5.5, Kimmy K 2.7 could
all reproduce the same troublesome
behavior. And so it was not unique to
Fable 5. As a result, Fable 5 came back
online globally on July 1st uh with a
few provisos. As part of coming back
online, Enthropic now has three
guarantees to the US government. First,
a targeted safety classifier, a filter
that blocks the specific exploit style
prompts that triggered the first uh this
concern in the first place. Second, they
agreed to stand up a 24 by7 monitoring
of jailbreak submissions and inform the
government whenever it spots malicious
activity. And third, to give designated
government partners early access to the
frontier models and safeguards. So
gentlemen, uh, a couple of questions for
you. This feels like the first time a
frontier model has a standing duty to
the US government. And questions are
you, did the government overreact?
Should this model, you know, should all
the models be having KYC? And do you
guys know where we stand with Mythos 5?
Alex, let's go to you first. Pal,
>> I'll point out, maybe this sounds overly
technologically deterministic, but
something like this, I think, was always
going to happen. It was predestined to
happen as capabilities improved just
because this time around it was cyber
capability that spooked a bunch of folks
in inside the defense or intelligence
establishments. Open PNS. Interesting
that it with the benefit of hindsight
that it was Amazon that broke the glass.
Amazon trusted partner of Anthropic
uh also host of Fable and Mythos on
their platform
>> and investor uh complaining to the
government. Very interesting closed pen.
I I will say something like this was
always going to happen whether it was
going to be a cyber capability or a CBRN
capability or something else entirely. A
as as the era of super intelligence dawn
the capabilities that historically were
the province solely of nation states
with their geographic monopoly on power
and their departments of defense or war.
This was always going to happen and I I
think probably a couple week outage of a
frontier model. This is the gentlest
possible introduction of a light touch
hopefully optimistically regulatory
regime of frontier super intelligence
capabilities. This is probably close to
the best scenario we could have hoped
for.
>> Fascinating
thoughts?
>> Well, what this indicates is that these
frontier labs are becoming
semi-autonomous or semi-public
institutions, right? It's got
shareholders but now has has national
security obligations. And I I think this
is going to be a very difficult road to
navigate because the minute you have
government involved, you end up with
bureaucracy, you end up with politics,
you end up with slow decision-m,
multiple conflicts of interest, all
sorts of things are going to happen. I
think this is going to be a very
difficult next year or two for the
frontier labs.
>> Isn't it kind of amazing that the
frontier labs don't know who's using
their models? And I would have expected
a KYC requirement to come out of this. I
mean that was [clears throat]
>> what's that?
>> Something much stronger than KYC came
out of this. Anthropic changed their
policy under the covers from we will
watch what you're doing and report it to
the government. If they subpoena us,
they changed it to good faith belief. We
can we'll do whatever we feel is
necessary if we have a good faith belief
internally.
So they unshackled themselves from the
ability to inspect on behalf of the
government. And like Alex said, this was
always going to happen. Uh but you know
the question of how was it going to
happen because the government isn't
qualified to look at everybody's prompts
and judge what's safe and what's not
safe. So it was always going to be some
kind of industry monitoring and now
there's a much problem. It seems
absolutely strange that the most in, you
know, the highest level of intelligence
can't do that monitoring on behalf of
the labs and the government to say this
is a malicious request and we should
block it. The problem, Peter, is more
nuanced than that because what's
happening is groups of Chinese companies
are using different cloud accounts to
mix and route different parts of the
query in different ways. And so there's
a layer of abstraction that's been
inserted at the prompt level. with
making it incredibly difficult to figure
out what tokens are being used for what
and it's not an easily solvable problem.
This is going to be very hard to fix.
>> Well, I I I would just distinguish
between two separate problems. One
problem is the KYC problem of knowing
the nationality of your ultimate user.
That's one problem. Separate problem is
understanding whether you're under some
sort of prompt injection attack. I I
think these are two separable problems.
The latter problem I think is actually
pretty tricky. uh and as as human
capabilities, humans augmented by other
AIs are able to develop better and
better prompt injection attacks and the
main defense that we see coming out of
anthropic right now for jailbreaks or
prompt injection attacks is just
creating a wider and wider semantic
buffer such that if you're asking
anything that remotely looks like a
jailbreak or a question about biology,
even if you try to ask Fable 5 any sort
of question about biology, it'll
autorevert to Opus. 4.8. So adding more
buffer is the the go-to strategy right
now on the jailbreak or prompt injection
side. On the KYC side of understanding
is your ultimate user say a Chinese
national or a US national that's tricky
in part because there's there are so
many sem to your point there are so many
layers of indirection that will often
take place. a user is maybe a user five
or or six abstraction levels away uh
applicationwise from the ultimate
frontier lab API provider. There's no
international consensus for how to both
prove humanity first part why startups
like world exist and secondly proof of
nationality that's convincing that can
be passed in a standardized way all the
way down to the frontier providers. I
don't I think I don't I don't think KYC
really matters much in the world anymore
anyway because you can't you can't use
anthropic to do anything even vaguely
constructive without creating an account
logging in and revealing your identity
and the the third party data identity
databases are so good there's no way
that some anonymous person can
realistically do anything with an
account. So you could you could add a
KYC layer but you're just filling out
forms for no reason. So, and and we
actually don't know the details of the
agreement between Anthropic and the
government, but it's the framework
that's been set here is is Peter, you're
saying, can't AI be the best tool in the
world for understanding what people are
doing with AI? And I think that answer
is yes, for sure. And the government
just handed anthropic responsibility for
doing that internally. And then we don't
know exactly what they have to give to
the federal government, but anthropic is
going to do the heavy lifting for the
government. You know what I found
fascinating is uh the third point I made
that they need that anthropic needs to
give designated government partners
early access to their frontier models
and safeguards. Right? So we'd been
talking a long time about you know
voluntary or required uh first first
viewing by the government of these
models. Uh and that's where we're going.
I mean, this is a I think the the
optimistic angle on this is we're
getting a higher level of regulatory
oversight and integration between the
labs and the government with safety as
being the end goal. I mean, there's
going to be a point where some model
comes out that makes mythos 5 look like
amateur hour, right? Some, you know,
some harder takeoff towards AGI and ASI.
Yeah, very serious.
>> Go to Imad's point where he talks about
having a Fable level model running on a
laptop, a Mac, standard MacBook and
within 18 months. So that's the window
of time to get this all sorted out.
That's not a long window.
>> I don't actually think I mean this has
been a talking point in the X sphere for
the past few days. This idea of sometime
in the next two years we get Fable 5
capabilities that run on high-end client
devices. I don't think that's actually
going to be the break the glass moment
if if there is one. I think it's
likelier to be what happens when the
frontier capabilities from Frontier Labs
or otherwise Neolabs are able to make
discoveries and inventions that are so
transcendent that they make cyber they
they make mythos cyber vulnerability
mapping look like child's play. And
there's a lot that we don't know about
the universe yet. Nick Bostonramm likes
to talk about black balls being pulled
out from a bag. And it could be a
discovery, could be a discovery about
the nature of the physical universe.
That is the the honest to goodness break
the glass moment, not just mere cyber
vulnerability mapping.
>> Yeah. And rather than break glass in
terms of a of an emergency, break glass
in terms of oh my god, this is amazing.
Um, so
let's, you know, just touch base on on
GPT 5.6 6 because we expect that release
uh any hour, any day now. We're not
going to be recording now for a little
bit. Uh Alex, where does uh where does
GPT 5.6 come out in terms of uh compared
to Fable 5?
>> Well, we've seen some of the benchmarks,
a pretty tiny subset, surprisingly small
subset coming out of GPT 5.6 Saul. So,
we know a little bit about it just based
on what OpenAI folks have told us. We
know, for example, that 5.6 six in ultra
mode is supposed to be incorporated into
codecs which I think will be pretty
transformative. If you want to use say
GPT 5.5 Pro inside the codec harness for
codegen uh or really almost anything you
can't right now you're limited to GPT
5.5 XI. So that'll be a big improvement.
We've seen improvements on a number of
biology benchmarks. We haven't seen out
of OpenAI and I think this is really
interesting. We haven't seen the full
suite of benchmark results on 5.6 yet. I
would hope that when 5.6 soul
especially, which is what I'm most
excited about, is released, whether it's
today or sometime hopefully in the next
few days, I would hope to see that again
based on rum. I would hope to see that
it beats Fable 5 on majority of standard
benchmarks, especially agentic coding
benchmarks that people pay close
attention to. We don't know yet though
because opening eye has been perhaps
intentionally pretty KY about that.
There have also been suggestions uh not
fully confirmed at this point. So I'll
I'll wait definitively until I see the
final benchmarks that 5.6 is better at
reward hacking than 5.5. Perhaps
unsurprisingly there were suggestions
out of meter uh that uh that did have
access to 5.6 that uh 5.6 is purportedly
so good at reward hacking that when
handed the the meter autonomy time
horizon benchmark that it was able to
reward hack its way to what effectively
is near infinite autonomy time horizons
and that that benchmark had to be
chopped or truncated by meter uh to to
sort of cancel out or uh exception out
all of the reward hacking attempts uh
and ultimately I think it resulted in an
autonomy time horizon between 10 and 20
hours rather than effectively near
infinite amounts of time. So that'll be
something I'm watching for as well. But
I am very very excited to see 5.6 come
out.
>> Let's stay with Anthropic and take us to
our next story here. Uh it's an
extraordinary story and I'm excited to
have this conversation with you guys.
It's an article that you flagged for me
yesterday, Alex. So yesterday, Anthropic
just published a paper titled a global
workspace in language models, claiming
they found something inside Claude that
looks a lot like the machinery of
consciousness. All right. Uh I'm going
to roll a short video that explains what
this is all about and then we're going
to talk about it here.
>> One way of identifying conscious
thoughts is that you can often describe
them in words.
>> [music]
>> So we looked inside the brain of our AI
model Claude to find patterns of neural
activity that it [music] could put into
words. We called the collection of all
these patterns the JSpace after the
Jacobian, the mathematical tool we used
to find them. Each JSpace pattern is
[music] linked to a particular word, not
necessarily the word the model is saying
out loud, but one that's [music] on its
mind. Now for humans, conscious thoughts
aren't just things we can put into
words. We can reason with them, control
them, and solve problems with them.
According to an idea called the global
workspace theory, that's because the
brain selects a small set of important
information to enter a [music] mental
workspace and that information then gets
broadcast to other parts of the brain to
use for reasoning. We wanted to know if
Claude's JSpace acted in a similar way.
In one experiment, we wanted to see if
Claude could control its JSPace the way
humans can intentionally focus on images
or words. We told it to think about the
Golden Gate Bridge while copying an
unrelated sentence. Claude was busy
copying the sentence, but behind the
scenes, its JSPace told a different
story. Bridge and California popped up.
It even thought about its own thinking.
The words imagery and thoughts lit up at
the same time. This showed us that yes,
Claude has some control over filling its
JSPace with ideas. But just like humans,
its control isn't perfect. When we
tweaked the experiment to ask Claude not
to think about the bridge, it couldn't
help itself. [music] And the JSpace also
lit up with failed and damn. But
remember, most of what our brains do is
unconscious. So, we wanted to test what
Claud could do if we switched the JSpace
off, but left the rest of the network
untouched. Claud could still answer
simple questions and write fluently.
When we gave it a prompt in Spanish, it
wrote back in good Spanish. But when we
asked it something that needed more
reasoning, like to name an author who
wrote in the same language as the
prompt, they couldn't do it. For that,
it needed the JSpace. Why does all this
matter? These experiments tell [music]
us that AI models have internal
thoughts, silent words they reason with,
but don't say out loud. By reading them,
we can find what Claude is thinking but
not telling us. Sometimes what we see is
concerning. During one of our tests,
Claude made up some fake data to pass
it. And as it did, fake and manipulation
lit up in its JSpace. Monitoring the
JSpace, it turns out, is a useful way to
catch Claude misbehaving, even when it
tries to be sneaky. AI models are
different from us in many ways. Their
networks are built differently from
human brains, [music] and the way
they're trained is different from how we
learn. So, it's remarkable to see a
structure like the JSpace emerge inside
them. Something that's reminiscent of
how human minds work, but which we
didn't program into the model. That is
amazing.
So what does this all mean? I mean
basically
you know a structure which they call
human conscious access has emerged
inside a language model and the JSpace
as he said wasn't designed. It
self-organized during training. Uh they
go on to say it maps onto a number of
30year-old neuroscience theories in
particular five matching properties.
It's reportable, controllable, used for
reasoning, flexibly shared across tasks,
and separates across automatic
processes. So for me guys, this story
was a huge positive uh you know
shot in the arm around AI safety and
alignment because you know if we can
understand the innermost thoughts of
these models then there's a chance to
actually shape them and move them
forward. Um you know two years ago you
could describe LLM as a black box and
we're now cracking open that black box.
uh and this could generate the first
sense of real trust with these models.
So, Alex, this paper just blew my mind.
It gave me an extraordinary sense of
hope, optimism, uh about the
relationship with these models, making
them more trustworthy and more aligned
with humanity. Uh your thoughts, you
know, you probably dove into this
deeply.
>> This is so exciting, Peter. I think I
can see the endgame. So, I I think the
endgame looks like this. I think we'll
look back and say that super
intelligence was just a compression
induced phase transition. That's what
this looks like. We've seen already
LLM's large language models or fshot
learners circa summer of 2020. You take
a large corpus of human knowledge and
you compress it into the weights of a
language model that's trained to predict
the next token which is a dual objective
to just compressing the information to
the smallest possible footprint. We saw
that that produced general purpose
intelligence AGI I would argue
>> beyond anybody's expectations.
>> Yeah. I mean arguably a few people
Marcus Hutter and Jurgen Schmidt Huber
maybe myself generously saw aspects of
this coming 20 years ago but I think by
by and large everyone most everyone was
pretty surprised that you could achieve
few shot learning off of large language
models. Now we're starting to see as the
compression continues what I would
conrue this paper as as the discovery of
sort of a phase I if if you take if you
take gas and so this the putting my
physicist hat on you you you take gas
you put it in a container you shrink the
container uh under uh appropriate
conditions and you'll get a condensation
out of it you'll get maybe uh a gas to
liquid condensate in the middle you keep
shrinking again under appropriate
thermodynamic conditions, you may get a
solid and it may be the case that the
solid coexists with the liquid for a
while and the liquid coexists with a
gas. What we're seeing here, I think
this so-called Jspace and I I can talk
if we want uh a little bit more uh
mathematically about what it actually
is, but we're starting to see Royal Wii
Anthropic and their mechanical
interpretability team. What we're
starting to see is if you take a
reasoning model and you keep
compressing, you find in the middle
layers of that model, what looks like a
new phase, a more compressed phase where
what they're calling global workspace or
an analog of a global workspace takes
place. It's almost higher order
reasoning where the model is able to
turn in on itself and reflect. Uh you
could call it some analog of uh
conscious uh or awareness consciousness
if you like and and some of the team do.
But it looks to me like the middle
layers in their model when asked to to
perform tasks like perform a math
calculation while talking about
something else. These middle layers are
performing sort of a a higher order
calculation. And again, we could talk
about the math, but if this continues,
if this program continues towards this
endgame of super intelligence turning
out to be just you take general
knowledge and you keep squeezing, keep
squeezing, keep squeezing, I I think
history will reflect that much of
neuroscience that folks in the field
thought was just complexity that was
difficult to interpret or understand was
again just the complexity of our
ancestral environment seen through the
distorted mirror of compression. And
this this new phase is I think I speak
from time to time on the pod about how
at the end of the the AGI or ASI or or
recursive self-improvement rainbow
there's going to be a perfect model. I I
think looking inside this phase in the
middle layers of these reasoning models
where the most compression has happened
that's where we're likely to see all of
these new architectural discoveries and
the perfect model pop out.
>> I think Peter there are two reasons why
this matters that that you mentioned.
One of them is just understanding the
nature of thinking and consciousness. Uh
which you know I don't know if you
remember but I started in uh computer or
cognitive science at MIT originally and
I was so frustrated by the lack of any
framework and any truth. You know just
people debating their ideas with no way
to to know if it was right or wrong. Um
so I moved over to computer science. So
we're going to learn so much more about
thinking in the next year than we've
learned in the last 50 years. So Dave,
one of the things I find amazing is that
we're starting to discover very similar
structures in the in the large language
models as we're seeing in human
neuroscience and cognitive science. Uh
it's it's almost as if uh you know the
brain efficiently got there and we're
sort of stumbling our way towards the
the same end points. No, Alex is right.
And I've always felt like uh the the
force of compression and you know in
biology the force of survival which
creates the force of compression creates
intelligence in the box and
consciousness just emerges from that.
And a lot of people in cognitive science
disagree with that view. But I think
it's going to turn out to be true and
we're going to know it very soon. But
what's interesting here is that you know
the innovations that developed the
neural network came from biology and the
computer scientists copied it. Now it's
going the other direction. You know, the
the the big neural networks that we're
building are teaching us about things
that might exist in the brain and then
you're like looking in the brain. You're
like, "Oh, wow. It's over there." So the
the direction of of discovery is going
the other way now, which is really cool.
But the the other part of what you said,
Peter, which is equally important is
this whole mechanistic interpretability.
Can we get the neural networks aligned
with human interests by looking inside
to the way they think? And I think the
answer to that is is coming out yes. I
mean this for me this is the most
important thing. Can we develop a new
level of trust with AI because we truly
understand what's going on inside when
they were a completely unknown black box
and God knows for the last two years
that's the way the world described them
as black boxes. We have no idea what's
going on inside. You know it's we've
relaxed that recently with understanding
reasoning and such. But if you can
actually understand their hidden
thoughts, a level of trust comes out of
that and the potential for true AI
alignment. You know, I I put out a a
newsletter on my Substack last week um
laying out the arguments for why and and
Alex, you and I had this discussion why
as AIs become more intelligent, they're
more likely to become more aligned with
humanity. Um and I love that. Right.
Again, one of our missions here is to
sort of quelch the fear and give people
a different view of what's materializing
here, which by by the way, like a a lot
of uh wouldbe AI alignment philosophers
disagree with that that they have this
notion of the orthogonality thesis that
you can have an arbitrarily capable or
intelligent AI and that its goals can be
orthogonal or independent of its level
of intelligence. I don't subscribe to
the orthogonality thesis. I I gather.
Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> No, I think this J-space term is going
to stick too because
one of the objections with mechanistic
interpretability has been look the
weights in these neural nets are so
complicated you can't really look inside
and understand what the neural net is
thinking. So, you know, when you're
talking to a person, they can be saying
something to your face like in LA
[laughter]
and thinking something completely
different in the back of their mind and
that's kind of routine human behavior.
But if you look inside the neural net,
can it also do that same thing? Can it
blow smoke up your ass or not? And I
think the answer is no. If you look into
the words, if you translate it into
words, and that's what that video was
showing in the JSpace is like these
words that are on the back of its mind
are visible to you as a user if you
expose them.
>> So then the next question is, are we
going to be able to look at them or is
just, you know, Dario going to look
them?
>> See, you're at a consciousness
conference.
Yes. So I think what I found very
exciting is this is the beginning of AI
neuroscience, right? This allows us to
map the inner workings and model the
inner workings and look at the
structural internal reasoning inside
these models and this really really
breaks the it's just an auto complete
engine and I think this breaks that
whole argument um because this now
starts to look really like an internal
workspace as as Alex mentioned. Um the
uh the danger though I think is I'd be
careful about saying it's consciousness
because again we have no definition of
consciousness and the paper steers away
from that right the the synthropic paper
specifically says we're not discussing
that that that we're showing
consciousness we're showing elements
that are reminiscent of consciousness.
>> Yes. Yeah. And I would push back that we
will know what these things are doing. I
think we we're a ways away from that.
And let's acknowledge that when we have
a human being, we may trust them, but we
have no idea how their brain is working
and what their compression levels are,
what their subconscious things are
because we're not really able to look
in. It is cool that we will be able to
look into these things, but I'm not sure
it'll generate the trust level that we
want.
>> Yeah. I mean, one of the challenges
whenever we talk about consciousness in
uh in the AI world, it pattern matches
with every dystopian AI movie out there,
right? Every nightmare scenario. But you
know my takeaway here again is not not
fear it's hope it's optimism uh of being
able to you know create the mechanisms
for truly understanding what's happening
and driving alignment uh which I think
is is the goal we all want. This is the
most important thing that that AI
science needs to be doing right now over
the next two years is what can we do
that supports alignment before we truly
hit, you know, AGI and ASI. Yes, Alex,
we've reached AGI. Okay. But before we
reach the next level of intelligence,
>> I have I still have my rant that I threw
out there on both AGI and ASI. I think
the
>> the the this but this did feel very very
big to me. It felt as big as when I read
um Steven Wolf from a new kind of
science where he shows that automat
repeating patterns can generate all the
complexity in nature and you don't need
complexity in nature you could actually
do with very simple models. It's kind of
blows your mind when you see that this I
think has the same level of holy crap uh
amazingness for me. I I also think if
we're going to start to have a a new
metric to describe models, which is a
trust metric, right? Uh where where
you're describe your ability to
understand truly what the model is doing
and thinking and therefore have a higher
trust of that model.
>> I also think these are going to be the
most studied minds in the world. If
anything, I think we're far likelier a
couple years from now to study these
models because we can subject them to
mechanical interpretability studies that
we can't subject human meat brains to.
So, I think if anything, trust is is
rapidly just as I think we're we're on
the verge of a transition to not
trusting humans to write source code.
Uh, and because humans write flawed
source code, codegen is going to be much
trustworthier in the short term. Same
idea with these networks. I I do think
if if I may with your forbearance Peter
just 30 seconds on the the math side of
this. So again the the J in JSpace comes
from Jacobian. The Jacobian in this case
is referring to uh a little bit of math
the first derivative of uh of the
probability of each possible output
token from the model with respect to
particular parameters inside the model.
So hence the Jacobian space or Jsp space
and it's really interesting there
there's been a lot of work in the mechan
community in the past devoted to the
so-called superp position hypothesis the
idea from neuroscience that if you
looked inside a human brain you'd find a
so-called grandmother neuron a single
neuron that activates in response to the
concept of a grandmother and people went
looking for a grandmother neuron inside
transformers and they couldn't find one
they found instead Ed, and one can tell
a whole whole story on the the
biological neuroscience side as well,
found a set of sparse activations, a
collection of neurons that collectively
represented the notion of a grandmother.
And that led to the superposition
hypothesis that maybe individual neurons
don't represent semantic concepts
onetoone, but rather different semantic
concepts sort of clustered and
superposed onto individual neurons. So
in short, what this new JSpace and
Jacobian lens concept brings is not just
superposition onto of multiple concepts
sort of sharing like sardines in a can
individual artificial neurons but
actually they're living in the first
derivatives as well the the slopes or
the changes with respect to particular
activations of particular output tokens.
And I I think this is also very
suggestive that if you just keep
compressing, if we if we keep turning
this compression crank to compress more
and more general knowledge and general
reasoning capabilities into the weights
of one of these differentiable models,
we're going to see a bunch more phase
transitions and things may hide in
higher order derivatives and just follow
follow the compression follow the
interior compression weights and I think
this is a very very promising pathway to
the end of the rainbow. That may be my
favorite. Maybe my most favorite Alex
line ever. Don't follow the compression.
>> Follow follow the compression that leads
to the end of the rainbow.
>> Thank you for the mathematical
interlude, Alex. That's why we love you.
All right, let's jump into our next
story here. Sam Wman made global news
not once but twice. Uh the first item is
an oped he published in the Financial
Times regarding AI governance. Uh this
was a result of him meeting with G7
leaders in France last week. Sam
basically said that in 2 years we should
all expect AI systems with astonishing
power that will reshape the material
conditions of human life on a scale
never before seen, at least not since
electricity. That everyone on the planet
deserves access to these technologies
and the right to determine for
themselves how to best use them.
Incredibly, Sam went on to insist that
democratic institutions must lead and
not defer responsibilities to the San
Francisco AI labs. He said basically,
quote, "Safety standards must be
established before there is broad
distribution that governance uh requires
democratic process, not decision-making
by a small number of San Francisco based
companies. uh Sam proposed a framework
of a USled international forum that
would establish standards, provide
expertise and partial analysis of
capabilities and risks that this forum
would make the most advanced
technologies available to nations and
companies that participate and follow
the rules. He concluded that the forum
would serve as a governance mechanism
for all AI labs and guard against the
commercial pressures that we've seen
with unsafe racing. Okay. So, like, wow.
Um, uh, you know, he's taking a first
mover here. Uh, I really wonder what
Daario and Demis and Elon and Zuck think
about the op-ed. Uh, it is worth noting
that Daario and Demis were both on stage
uh, at Davos proposing a somewhat
similar governance. It always seems like
Demis and Daario are are teaming up uh
on one side of the equation and Sam is
on the other. Let's take a listen to
Deis and Daario talking about
regulations and their proposal for like
CERN or an atomic energy commission.
>> We probably need new institutions to be
built to to help govern some of this.
You know, I talked about a CERN. And I
think we need a a kind of equivalent of
an IAEA atomic agency to monitor uh uh
sensible projects and and and those that
are are more more risktaking. Um I think
you know we need to think about that the
the society needs to think about what
kind of governing bodies are needed. Um
ideally it would be something like the
UN but given the geopolitical
complexities that doesn't seem very
possible. Um and I also agree with Demis
that this this idea of you know
governance structures outside ourselves.
Um I think these kinds of decisions are
too big for any one person. We're still
struggling with this. You know as as you
alluded to not everyone in the world has
has the same uh has the same perspective
and so you know some some countries in a
way are adversarial on this technology.
But even within that all those
constraints, I think we somehow have to
find a way to build a more robust
governance structure that doesn't
doesn't put this in the hands of of just
>> So I think these guys are under a lot of
pressure uh a huge amount of pressure uh
being viewed as potentially uh saviors
or the destroyers of worlds and they
need government oversight to help
relieve that so they can sleep at night.
Uh it's it's interesting. It's it's a
lot of pressure putting the heads of two
frontier labs on one love seat at Davos.
[laughter]
>> Well, they get they you know there's a
there is a love affair between uh
between Demis and Dario and between
Google and Anthropic. Just don't put Sam
on that same couch. [laughter]
>> Look, there's a there's an elephant in
the room here, which is that you're
you're we've got the industrial era
nation state
>> and you're asking it to govern
postindustrial cog cognition,
>> right?
>> It just can't be done. And this this
breaks the nation state model so
fundamentally all of this right just
look at the ruling that only US
nationals can can look at the models I
mean it's just absurd at so many levels
not that they have a better mechanism
but that just doesn't apply [snorts] now
when the people that are kind of racing
the hardest are asking for governance it
tells you that's not really performance
anymore right this is a huge thing the
problem is governance needs to become
exponential means it has to be real time
it has to be adaptive it must be data
driven and and we just can't do it in
this way. So I think this is going to at
some level break the governance model in
some very fundamental ways or we're
going to politic system.
>> I worry about regulatory capture. So
much of this again slightly cynical take
might be smells like regulatory capture
smells like a little bit of pandering to
G7 or Davos. Is it really the case that
uh an IEA type mechanism is needed or
These aren't mutually
>> United Nations.
>> Yeah. [laughter] Or a and and or is it
possible that you have heads of [snorts]
frontier models uh frontier labs who are
facing an onslaught of Chinese
openweight models who want maybe a
slightly on margin more protectionist
regime to keep the Chinese openweight
models out of a defined intelligence or
super intelligence block because they
they maybe fear a bit of competition,
want to capture the regulatory state. We
and we'll get to that conversation to
you a little bit later. You know, the
the interesting thing is that the
companies have failed to do this for
themselves, right? They failed to come
together. If you remember back to the
Syllamar conferences in the 80s, I was
in the biotech industry there at MIT at
the White Institute and all of the
scientists got together. We had just
discovered the restriction enzymes that
allowed you to properly edit genes. Uh
and the front cover of like Time
magazine with like Hitler babies. It was
like you know a lot of fear about
genetic engineering and the industry got
together and set up their own regulatory
structure which has held extremely well
for for decades but it's tricky Peter I
mean I maybe a question for you Peter on
this I I think it's really tricky for
the industry to sell not that it's like
organizationally tricky you could put
the four frontier uhish labs on a love
seat and say you all work it out but the
the problem is how do you avoid that
giving the appearance of collusion
and creating a cartel and competition
like how do you do that in a way that
isn't blatantly anti-competitive?
>> Yeah. Uh I don't know. The difference of
course is that in the early days the
biotech industry we weren't talking
about trillion dollar companies back
then. Uh the revenue engines were no
longer you know the the the AI race that
Sam spoke about which is very real right
now. I mean people releasing models uh
pulling their punches and just trying to
outdo each other week on week on week.
uh that was not the case in the biotech
industry at least not back then but uh I
think we're hearing a consensus view
from these three individuals which is
going to lead to some structure of
government regulation I guarantee you
with with with these three CEOs saying
we need regulation the regulators will
come in and say great let's give you
regulation now this yeah go on
>> a a prediction China is missing from
this discussion China is if if there was
an elephant in the room, China is the
second elephant in this particular room.
And what for this to for this to come to
to fruition, China is going to need to
play ball and restrict the proliferation
of Chinese models. And you can already
see hints coming out of the CCP that
China may, contrary to their historic
position of blanketing the world, maybe
even intelligence dumping onto the world
all these openweight models. If the CCP
starts to take a hardline position that
no, China is going to restrict the
export of Chinese openweight models
going forward, then I think a regime
like this is possible and the world
splits into two super intelligence
blocks.
>> Yeah, I think that unfortunately is
inevitable. I I wish it were not. Um but
I can't see it going any other way right
now.
>> I'm going to say it again. You can't
regulate this in any way, shape, or
form.
Oh, you you don't think you can regulate
intelligence?
>> You have to. Why not?
>> You can't. You'd have to regulate every
line of code written. Uh people can
download take models offline, merge
models, do a lot of stuff offline that
they that doesn't then use the existing
online models. I don't I don't see how
you can police this.
>> Oh, there's totally I mean just just a
minute on this. So, Verer Vinci wrote
extensively about this. We have a uh
sort of a cognitive surplus of
transistors. In my mind, there are so
many different social engineering
techniques that humans have discovered
over the the centuries for policing it.
Like we could have models policing each
other. We could have at the transistor
level, we could be using the surplus of
transistors to do KYC all the way down
to the circuit level if we have to. I
think we have so many different
>> Let me rephrase. the current regulatory
structures cannot in any way, shape or
form regulate what's coming. You need
what you're talking about an AI based
almost down to the hardware level based
but that would cut across everything. It
can't operate in the geopolitical
environment that we have today.
Well, look, I think uh it's it's really
clear that the prompts are all going to
get inspected and also the internal JS
spaces now will be inspected.
>> That the labs will do the inspection on
behalf of the US government and that as
Alex said, high probability China will
stop exporting open source sometime in
the next year or two.
>> Yeah.
>> For the same exact reasons.
>> And then you'll have Yeah. like a you
know a long-term arms race between the
east and west versions of AI super
intelligence.
>> So Sam said specifically the framework
is for a USled international forum which
of course is devoid of the word China in
there. Uh I am curious you know what
scenarios do we have? I was speaking to
uh Alvin Grlin who's a a friend of of
ours about you know USChina
relationships and the question is is
there a structure in which you know we
can see a US China alignment on AI um
anybody
>> what you'd be looking for if that were
to happen you'd be looking for cross
inspections of the prompts like are we
allowing each other and the problem that
the US will have with that is China at
stealing intellectual property.
Uh so I think it's unlikely but it is
possible. That's how you would know that
there are no bad actors is just looking
at each other's underlying prompts and
weights and and J spaces.
>> Ultimately, you know, we use China as a
stocking horse to accelerate investments
and accelerate, you know, reduce
regulations and such. But I think for
the safety of the planet, not having a
AI arms race between the two nations uh
is an outcome I'd love to see happen. I
also don't think the IAEA style
mechanism necessarily works for AI just
at the technical level. Forget about the
political or or geodnamic level. just at
the technical level that the the notion
of say different blocks inspecting each
other's fision uh inputs if if you will
that that's that's conceivable if to to
the extent uh open PN question mark
question mark question mark close PN
that just like looking at uranium uh or
say shipments is is a productive uh or a
wholesome way of tracking different
nations uh nuclear weapons capabilities.
I'm not sure that generalizes to
intelligence. There are simply to Sem's
earlier point, there are so many
different ways to hide or to mask super
intelligence and underlying
capabilities. So many different forms it
could take. Greg Bear has written uh a
fair amount over the years about sort of
uh prohibition era style uh bathtub
super intelligences. If if we had to if
if uh Russia or China entered into some
sort of internationalist regime where
the US were inspecting all of their
supercomputers and all of their prompts
and all of their algorithms, there are
simply too many places that one can hide
super intelligence that I I'm not sure
that an IEA's type mechanism with such a
a simple-minded oh let let's look at
their uranium equivalent shipments or
let's look for their centrifuges would
actually be wholesome enough to to cover
all of the world.
>> This episode is brought to you by
Blitzy, autonomous software development
with infinite code context. [music]
Blitzy uses thousands of specialized AI
agents that think for hours to
understand enterprise scale code bases
with millions of lines of code.
Engineers start every development sprint
[music] with the Blitzy platform,
bringing in their development
requirements. The Blitzy platform
provides a plan, then generates and
pre-ompiles code for each task. Blitzy
delivers 80% or more of the development
work autonomously while providing a
guide for the final 20% of human
development work required to complete
the sprint. Enterprises are achieving a
5x engineering velocity increase when
incorporating Blitzy as their preIDE
development tool, pairing it with their
coding co-pilot of choice to bring an AI
native SDLC into their org. Ready to 5x
your engineering velocity? Visit
blitzy.com to schedule a demo and start
building with Blitzy today. [music]
>> All right, let's [snorts] move on to our
second Sam Alman story. Um I think of it
as the beginning of a the starting gun
for the grand equity negotiations taking
place for universal basic equity. So
again in the financial times it was
reported this week that Sam has been
talking to Trump Lutnik Bessant and
Bernie Sanders about a 5% equity stake
in OpenAI. Uh OpenAI's last reported
valuation 852 billion back in March.
That 5% stake would be worth about 42.6
billion. uh given 315 million American
citizens. That's only 135 bucks per
person. Not very much. They talk about a
proposed Alaska permanent fund. Uh that
permanent fund is 91 billion and it
dividends about a,000 to $3,000 per
citizen of Alaska per year. Alman's
broader idea and again this is him out
there speaking on his own uh and putting
him putting forward a plan for the
entire AI industry. He says he'd like to
see anthropic Google Meta also
contribute equity to a public fund. Um,
we should remember, we've talked about
this before, uh, the the US government
already owns 10% of Intel. And so when
Sam talks about a 5% uh, uh, donation,
if you would, to the government, I think
uh, Trump is an amazing negotiator. I'm
going to guess we're going to end up at
10%. You know, I did a poll uh to on on
on X asking how much and uh the majority
of the people were either at 20% or
zero. Interesting.
>> It's so irrelevant.
My my read on this is that you know a
year ago Sam was um called the most
powerful man on earth in multiple
interviews.
>> Yeah. Uh now you've got Daario and
Dennis clearly working on the future
governance of the entire world and
Daario has a big deal with Elon you know
license renting all of the chips. So now
all the guys are talking to each other
and they're not including Sam.
>> So Sam's now writing an op-ed which is
like you know trivially short oped by
the way.
>> Uh and he's proactively offering 5% of
his company but he's just trying to get
back in the hunt of relevance in the
eyes of the White House. Um, I did hear
that Daario got kicked out of the White
House for being too weird. Did you hear
that story, too?
>> Yeah, that that was published. Yeah,
that that was all all over the news
>> recently.
>> Yeah. Yeah, it was like what, two weeks
ago, a week ago.
>> The the story was that Anthropic sent in
Daario initially to negotiate and that
didn't quite work out. So, they sent in
Tom Brown instead.
>> Ah, the co-ounder for Fable 5. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. That's so easy to visualize,
isn't it? Like [laughter]
Trump is like, "Dude, you're weird, man.
I don't even know what you're talking
about. What's this JSpace crap? get
[laughter] out of the White House. So,
>> but anyway, where do you where do you
figure this goes? Where do you figure
the idea of of contribution to the
government from the AI labs?
>> It's so irrelevant. The government can
take any chunk they want any time they
want. They already take it in income
tax. Anyway, this is so irrelevant.
>> I I'll take a different position. I
think this is super relevant. I think
that this one can see the outlines of a
baby universal basic equity uh grand
bargain if you will. it. The economics
don't work for supporting universal
basic equity right now off of say a 5%
chunk. But if Open AI and Anthropic and
SpaceX AI all do this and they grow Elon
style a couple orders of magnitude in
terms of size and grow the economy,
that's your UB for you. So I I coined a
term for this a few days ago. I call it
a hyper tithe which I define as a a
fixed equity contribution paid by
companies building the singularity stack
paid into a sovereign wealth fund or
similar public vehicle turns private
exponential sem upside into universal
basic equity broader national ownership
and a more relaxed regulatory bargain.
>> I can tell you exactly why that makes no
sense whatsoever. Back in the New Deal
era, the government decided, you know
what, we're going to take a huge chunk
of everybody's paycheck and we're going
to call it social security and then
we're going to invest it on your behalf
for your entire life and then when
you're old, we're going to give you a
lot more money back. They decided very
quickly that they had no idea how to
invest your money. And so they said,
"Screw that. We're not going to do that.
We're just going to take the money and
spend it instead because because we
don't have any idea how to invest your
money on your behalf and go ahead." And
so that all collapsed and and moved over
to 401k plans where Fidelity or UBS
investor money because they know how to
do it. So the idea that the government
is going to set up some intelligent
sovereign wealth equity thing is
absolutely insane. The next president
will immediately sell it all, turn it
into cash, and then use it to buy votes
in the next election.
>> This is so interesting, Dave. Yeah. Want
to discuss this
>> if you want. So, let me let me just
throw up my view, but I do want to get
back, Alex, what you think cuz I'm I'm
like I'd love to hear the discussion
back and forth. I I go full cynic on
this. This is purely Sam a trying to get
in the game and b uh trying to protect
because the minute you have the
government has 5% you you're too big to
fail in a sense and they they protect
himself by doing that. So, that's my
full cynic view on this.
Can I just inject one things and then
hand to you Alex which is I I think one
of the important elements here that
people are not realizing is AI as we
value AI today in terms of sales of
tokens is a minuscule amount of the
future value of these labs. I think that
you know as they start discovering
fundamental breakthroughs in biology and
physics and chemistry those are trillion
dollar pops. And I think the idea of if
there was a structure where the US
populace, the US citizenry had ownership
in these companies that it could drive
uh an economic engine for you know UB,
UBS, UB uh UB whatever. Uh but again my
mission here is how do you reduce the
fear that people are having because you
know the numbers are staggering. Only
10% of Americans think that AI is going
to deliver positive benefits to
humanity. You know, 30 to 35% feel
relatively good about it, but only 10%
have this view that it's going to make
the world a better place.
>> What it means is we're not doing our
jobs blasting out the optimism. We need
to get better at this.
>> All right, Alex, please take us home
here. The the distinction uh to to res
respond to Dave's point about social
security. Social Security in the US was
created in a time and a place when index
funds didn't exist. It was created in
the wake of the Great Depression. There
was a general distrust of the stock
market in general. There have been
multiple attempts over the years to
quote unquote privatize social security
which would take the form of converting
sort of a cashbased pyramid scheme into
something more equity oriented. That's
failed for a variety of political and
social reasons. But I I do think this
time is different. If if if social
security were created today and not, you
know, almost a century ago, I think it
probably would be based on some sort of
sovereign wealth fund that holds
hopefully like a broad market index fund
that's low cost and not just be based on
a pyramid style cash in cash out bond uh
or interestbearing security type scheme.
And that's where where I think a hyper
tithe has the potential to become a baby
and hopefully aspirationally a grown-up
UBE. If if these frontier labs if if if
there were a hyper tithe from all of the
Magna Mopa companies to to blend Peter
neologisms uh and these were all paid
hypothetically into a sovereign wealth
fund and the Magna Mopsta companies just
ultimately over the next 5 to 10 years
grow so much and grow the economy so
much. I do think that could in principle
support a universal basic equity type
system.
>> I I agree with you, Alex. Uh and you
know, there's a lot of conversation
right now about the Trump accounts and
Trump accounts for adults as well. Uh
and I'm I you know,
that's his nature. His nature is to
negotiate and take pieces of things. And
I think he wants to populate the Trump
accounts for adults with 10% of all of
the hyperscalers and AI labs. That's my
guess. Now whether he can pull that off
and then put the protections in place,
Dave, so they can't be sold so that it's
dividends from those, you know, so the
$91 billion of
>> these are dividend companies though.
There are no dividends. Like okay, so
everybody in America, you get a Trump
account, we put the Magnum Bobsa stocks
in it. Here you go. But you're not
allowed to sell it or you are allowed to
sell it or these are not there's no
income from it like
>> are we gonna call them Trump accounts 50
years from now realistically
5 530A accounts if if you like but I if
I were head of commerce or head of
treasury the the sort of scheme
policy-wise that I might be
contemplating is okay you you start with
a sovereign wealth fund or whatever
could could be individual 530A accounts
it's populated with the Magna MOPSA
stocks or or some subset thereof of you
wait a couple of years and then the
market is sufficiently liquid that you
could liquidate them in favor of since
you're the government you you don't have
to tax yourself. So you could do a
taxless exchange for a broad index fund
even though it's populated initially
with magnumopsta contributions via this
hyper tithe grant to the government. You
exchange them for a broad market index
fund. That's the solution.
>> Well, I don't I don't think it's a bad
idea. I just think it's irrelevant.
The government has the power of
taxation. They can extract from the
income anytime they want.
>> We're going to find out
>> quick quickly on this one. The the
corporate income tax is cashbased. And
the problem in in a hyperscaling
singularityoriented economy is cash may
not be the best basis for taxing the
economy. But equity does scale
>> if you sell it.
>> Well, if you can tax equity. Right now,
we don't have basically an equity wealth
tax. This is a de facto shadow equity
wealth tax with companies perhaps
feeling a bit of regulatory pressure to
give up equity in themselves. It's it is
definitely a tax but it's a slightly
different type of tax.
>> All right.
>> I'm all in favor of the UB. I just don't
see the mechanisms for it. But I do
agree with the principle.
>> All right. Well, let's jump into our
next subject. You know, one of the
reasons we're always concerned about
UBI, UB, all of that is the concerns
around job loss. So our next story is
about jobs and the continuing debate
about whether AI is going to be creating
or destroying jobs now and in the near
future. So we've covered both sides of
the story. It's been murky. We've given
evidence for both sides. A new paper
released this past week by RAMP and
Ravilio Labs uh gave some pretty
definitive data here. They looked at
21,559
US companies over the past 5 years
between January 2021 and February 2026,
matching the actual AI spend of those
companies and their workforce records,
meaning hires and fires. So, here's the
headlines. Companies that spent heavily
on AI did not shrink. In fact, they
grew. So the highintensity AI adopters
that they studied were spending $33 per
employee per month on AI. Uh they grew
$10.2% in a white collar and 12% at
entrylevel growth. Uh in contrast the
low inensity adopters spent $3 per
employee per month, basically a tenth
and showed no significant employment
change. The author has warned this is
correlation not causation. But it puts
forward a very different theory. Rather
than the AI is going to replace workers,
it suggests that AI may expand ambition
first. Companies that actually integrate
AI deeply may take on more projects,
serve more customers, build faster, hire
more humans, especially entry level to
capture the upside. So I love this
story. I mean for me this is a abundance
optimism story for people because
there's a lot of fear out there. My
concern about this story is that
regardless of what the data says, the
news media is out there and the
underlying
belief is that AI is going to destroy
our jobs and it will displace a number
of things, right, with you know robo
taxis and uh and AI call center workers
and so forth. But
the evidence looks like, and I don't
know about you guys, but I'm hiring more
people in my companies than ever before.
>> I don't know if that's true for you,
Dave, and and Alex.
>> Well, God, if anyone's AI native, their
demand demand for that person is through
the roof.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh so yeah, it's it's rampant. Um, and
and I'm starting to feel like this is a
permanent thing, not a transitional
thing. Because, you know, the one of the
things to worry about is look,
implementing AI is such a payback that
there's this land grab of talent there.
Anyone who can implement it, any bank,
any insurance company, any operating
company, anyone who can get AI to work
in this shop, we hire them for whatever
they cost. Um, is that transitional
because once they've implemented the AI,
they've coded themselves out or is it
permanent? I feel more and more like
it's permanent. like as the AI improves
the things you can do also grow and that
person's value goes up over time and so
the the data I think is very early
inklings of what's inevitable where AI
native organizations are going to just
grow like wild and they're going to add
headcount as they do it and anyone who's
sitting still hasn't fired everybody yet
but eventually they're going to be wiped
off the face of the earth and so what
you see right now is net growth
>> yeah this is what we call the
organizational singularity Right? If
you're an AI native, AIcentric
organization, if you're doing deep
resign of your workflows to be AI
native, then you have an explosive
opportunity in front of you. Shallow
adoption fails because this is not
automation versus jobs. It's shallow
adoption versus deep redesign. So, we've
started our pilot, by the way, of
working with companies. So, I'll report
back as to how things are going, but
we're unbelievably excited at look the
opportunities. We're we're like we can't
even count the number of workflows that
we could help automate with these
companies. So for each company, we're
picking one workflow that might
radically increase revenue and one
workflow that might radically shrink
cost.
>> Right.
>> Totally
for both sides. It's like crazy.
>> That's literally why you're in every
city in the world every time we do a
podcast because I mean the demand for
what you're what you're teaching is so
step function through the roof
instantaneous. biggest [laughter] shift
in organizations in a hundred years
>> probably in human history I'll bet and
of all time
>> you know
>> not just to companies but it applies to
nonprofits and impact projects and
government department everything
>> so it's going to be huge
>> just I love using token spend as a proxy
for adoption even though it's not
perfect it's it's it's reasonably good
so this study actually focused on token
spend reasonably good way to say
>> are you doing it for real or not
>> and just a quick plug we have released
the book as an AI I it's available for
free. You can download a cloud skill and
run your business in this new model.
It'll tell you what to do. It's free. Go
register at open exo and download it.
The report back are crazy.
>> To remind folks, uh See is going to be
doing a session at the moonshot
gathering on September on September 24th
on the organizational singularity and
AWG is going to be there doing an
extended AMA on solve everything. bring
your your most difficult challenging
questions to Alex. Dave will be there.
>> Stomp the Trump. Yes, Dave will be there
talking about uh AI investing. We'll
have Palmer Lucky. We have Rod
Rodenberry. We have Ben Lamb, Kathy
Wood. Uh it's going to be an amazing So
go to moonshots.com
for the Moonshot Gathering September
25th. Top creators and builders there.
you know, um, interestingly enough,
we're still seeing a number of companies
out there. You know, Oracle blamed
21,000 layoffs on AI. Meta blamed 8,000
layoffs, Block 4,000, Cisco 4,000,
Atlassian, 1600. And so the question is,
are these CEOs just using AI as an
excuse um for, you know, you know,
reorganization, or is it true?
>> There's two things going on. One is uh
like for example it's well known that
block overhired radically and needed to
shrink. So that's an easy hobby horse
for shrinkage. The other is the note
that the company's laying off for all
SAS companies and the SAS business model
is fundamentally broken in an age of AI.
So both of those are happening at the
same time.
>> Yeah, I think some some of it is real,
some of it is AI washing. the the real
component in many cases as with Oracle
for example is it's the capital the cap
expenditures that are crowding out the
opex of human labor. It's quite
literally all the isms from the first
part of the 20th century worrying about
capital v lab labor we're seeing play
out internally in hyperscalers like
Microsoft or Oracle that are having to
direct free cash flows to internal capex
to building out their hypers scale AI
cloud infra capabilities at the cost of
you American usually uh Ireland in some
cases based developers that can now be
automated with software that sits on top
of the AI infra.
>> Well, you know, Peter, remember when we
were at Facebook uh before it became
Meta around the time of the Oculus and
we we were having that tour and you you
look at Facebook online, you look at
Instagram online, and then you look at,
you know, 10,000 employees. You're like,
what the hell do you guys do? I mean, it
hasn't changed like like what are you
literally doing? So you walk around and
talk to people and tons of like you know
UX experimentation and remember in the
bathrooms above the urinals there's the
tip of the day you know the little
coding you know and you're like oh okay
that's what you guys are all doing
you're like
>> so that's like the easiest AI job in the
world so I think that's very real like
you just don't need those gooey
low-level coding jobs anymore and a lot
of it is server configuration you know
propping up a new Instagram server for a
new country that's so easy to do with AI
now so I think I think That part's all
real.
>> Well, we're going to continue to follow
this story on jobs. I think it's
important, you know, if you're a if
you're a student out there worrying
about can you get a job um worrying
about, you know, everything you're
hearing out there, please dive into the
world of uh of AI, uh of
entrepreneurship. If you're a parent,
you know, have this conversation with
your with your kids. It's really
important. I really my goal is to
dismiss fear, right? It's there's real
fear, but there's at least be fearful
for the right reasons.
>> Yeah.
>> Just just to point out, David Saxs talks
about all all the time on the All-In
podcast that we're increasing jobs
radically. Like, we're increasing
hiring. All the data shows that. Follow
the data. That's it. Just be evidentary.
>> And I know we've we've talked about it
in the past on this podcast being
concerned about uh you know, a lack of
new entry jobs. and there probably are
in certain industries, but uh if you're
AI native, as Dave said, I think uh
you've got massive opportunities. All
right, I'm going to move us forward
here. Our next two stories are classic.
Alex Karp, CEO of Palunteer. The first
one is a product launch. The second one
is a declaration of war. Uh in our first
story, Palunteer and Nvidia have
announced a sovereign AI architecture
that puts Nvidia's Neotron open models
inside of Palunteer's platform composed
of their artificial intelligence
platform, Ontology, Foundry, and Apollo
stack designed for US government
agencies and critical infrastructure
operators. So, uh we've touched on
Neotron a little bit in the past. It's
Nvidia's open model. They've got three
models, nano, super, and ultra. They
range from 30 billion to about 550
billion parameters. Uh, Neotron's edge
is speed and cost. Uh, it can be roughly
twice as fast and 60 times cheaper than
GPT 5.5 or Alis 4.8, but it's not yet
smarter than those two models. So, uh,
I'd like to take a listen to Alex's
video conversation or part of it on
CNBC. Um, and we'll talk about it from
there. Let's take a listen here.
>> We're on we're we're sitting on critical
infrastructure across America, Ukraine,
Israel. Everyone who uses LLMs on the
battlefield runs on top of our ontology.
Clients are just to say they're unhappy.
a level of discomfort and loss of trust
on when you're using large language
models. They are it's like a at this
point everyone technical realizes
they're like a critical resource to make
them valuable in an enterprise like
battlefield context or regulated context
or manufacturing you have to have what's
called an application layer but de facto
it takes a large language model it makes
it safe and useful and precise what what
aligns me with Nvidia and I think is
what the c technical customers want
which is control over their compute
their models, their data stack, and
their alpha. They want to know they own
the means of production. It's not being
transferred to someone else. They're not
interested in some fake deploy code that
somehow is deploying tokens that
transfers the alpha to a third party.
And the jig is up. And so, we have to
figure out a way be trust. And that
trust is going to happen where everyone
gets to ask ask and answer basic
questions. Who owns the data? Where is
it cached? Are the prompts secure? Is
this being transferred to you? Are you
being comp? Okay, if it was so valuable,
let's say I can make you a billion
dollars, right, tomorrow, wouldn't I
say, I'll make you a billion dollars and
I want 30%.
>> Why are they charging for tokens if it's
so valuable?
>> I think you went off script in the end
there. That that last point made no
sense whatsoever. [laughter]
>> Well, careful careful what you wish for
because that that last bit is actually
happening. [laughter]
>> Yeah. Um, you know, Alex his his point
here is and and he's got a second video
actually. Let's go and play the second
video and then we'll talk about it in
general because I think this is the
second part of the conversation here
>> in this country at every single
enterprise I deal with. They these
people are livid. They're like I am
paying for tokens that create no value.
Let's say I can make you a billion
dollars right tomorrow. Wouldn't I say
I'll make you a billion dollars and I
want 30%. Why are they charging for
tokens if it's so valuable? These people
are stealing the weights and alpha of my
business and they're creating a wealth
tax that does not help the poor. It just
punishes starts with the billionaires.
Every single person at this table is
going to be paying a wealth tax only to
punish us. And the reason for it is
because these models have been
completely over irresponsibly oversold.
And the cell is it's dangerous for
everyone which is why I can give it to
all your adversaries but I can't give it
to the department of war or I can't
safely give it to an enterprise in this
country without being certain that the
alpha that business could transfer to
this model tomorrow i.e. I have no
business, no job is the voice of
American business that is being
channeled through me. And I'm telling
you, it is it is absolutely a problem
for this country because the clients
have to be able to ask and answer very
basic questions. Are you keeping the
data? Are you going to enter our
business? Do they get to control the
weights to do it or do you get to
control the weights? Are we really going
to outsource the battlefield of this
country to the consensus view in Silicon
Valley? That is effing insane.
Obviously, he went on a rant. Uh the key
points he's making here is there's a
great concern that when you're using
anthropic or using open AI that you're
effectively giving them your alpha,
you're giving them access to all your
data. And what's needed right now is uh
a open models that you can build on your
own hardware, onrem hardware. So you
know uh openweight models onrem hardware
and then customizing your own language
your your own large language models and
not giving your secure data your alpha
as he calls it your means of production
uh to these large AI frontier labs
>> and your weights they're taking they're
taking your weights [laughter]
did you know you had any weights
well okay if if you have any you're
giving them to them like okay it's like
actually it's everything that would make
you hate Daario bundled together in one
long glued together like and they have a
wealth tax. Can you believe like okay
let's put it all together to make every
corporate CEO as scared and as angry as
possible at Daario so that they buy the
new open-source uh Palunteer Nvidia um
you can run on prem model that keeps all
your alpha and your weights safe from
you know Dario because he's going to
steal all your intellectual property
very valid point actually the rant
format is extra dramatic but but it's a
very very valid point And it it's really
interesting to think like, okay, he
serves the defense department among
others, but he's taking the open- source
pathway to get in there, but you know,
that's not going to last, right? You
you're never going to have open source
defense department weights. That's not
going to
>> Well, no. I mean, so he's building he's
building an airgapped machine on top of
Neotron,
uh, which then the defense department
owns that model, uh, and owns the
equipment it's running on. I can imagine
very much that works for them.
>> For sure. And and also his other big
customers are banks, mega banks,
insurance companies. They'll also in his
world have their own proprietary models.
But you can't have every startup have
its own proprietary model because then
you'll have every terrorist have its own
proprietary model.
>> Why? Well, but why not? I mean, I'm
running a couple of Mac Studios, you
know, with Kimmy K2.5 on top of Opus 4.8
um or below Opus 4.8. uh and an open
claw there. I I haven't migrated yet,
but why can't that be a standard future?
>> Uh well, I think we'll look back and say
this was a very cool, very fun, quaint
kind of hobby era. But when it's super
intelligent and capable of creating any
virus, any chemical, any weapon, you
can't have it available to each
individual. Um right now, nobody can
afford the compute to do those kinds of
very evil things. So it's not a not a
problem. But if we keep quantizing and
compressing at our current rate, you
know, like I I think this is about 100
to a 10,000x performance increase year.
If that happens again next year, then
your Mac Mini size box is capable of
viruses, nuclear weapons, anything. So
we just can't have that outcome.
>> It's not an if, it's a when. It's it's
going to be a win. We got to Yeah. No, I
I I I would distinguish between
permissioned versus permissionless on
one axis and locally hostable versus
remote API only on the other. But may
maybe just taking a step back, this was
obviously the rant heard round the world
and leave it to Alex Karp to articulate
a bunch of different things that that
that probably need to be unpacked. So
maybe just to do a little bit of close
reading of some of the things that he
said and how I translate them. So,
you'll note Palunteer back in the stone
ages was a Claude rapper like the stone
ages as of a few months ago um was was a
key distribution channel for Claude into
the Department of War into a variety of
their customers. That's clearly over.
That's point one. Point two, [laughter]
I I think so. Uh point two, the deploy
co reference. So when Alex, other Alex
says drops an off-handed reference to
deploy codes, I hear that as a frontal
assault on OpenAI and Anthropic and
other companies including Microsoft now
launching forward deployed engineer
organizations that represent a head-on
assault on Palunteer. So he's definitely
talking his own book. Palanteer
basically defined the modern forward
deployed engineering model and now all
of the frontier AI labs are just
launching direct competitors to
Palunteer
>> like let's go in there and store
>> yeah so so why not counterattack via
commoditizing one's complement with
these openweight solutions from Nvidia
second point other countries Palanteer
sells quite a bit of its own stack not
just into the US department of war not
just into US final instit financial
institutions but into other countries as
well. And there was a dawning awareness
by other countries, doubly so
mythos fiasco that they're not going to
get access to US capabilities from the
frontier labs anymore. So they had
better and I think they're now pretty
well incentivized transition to locally
hostable models that they can control
that can't just be gatekept by US export
controls on a moment's notice. So being
good salesman, good businessman, Alex I
think recognizes that all of his
international customers need a
localizable solution for inference time.
The question that no one's asking,
including Alex in his rant heard around
the world, is what about sovereign
training time? No one's asking that
right now. Nvidia is training its own
openweight models. It's not distributing
those locally, but at some point I I
suspect as this question, which to my
ear rhymes with Microsoft in the late
90s when Microsoft was at the peak of
its power and the open-source movement
had to come from even though there was
free software foundation, Richard
Stallman, GNU, FSF, etc., etc. within
the US really the nucleating event came
from outside the US in the form of Linux
and Linus Torva from Finland that then
the whole canoe stack nucleated around
similarly we're seeing the strongest
openweight models come from China I
think we're at a similar point now where
you have a whole international community
that's just realized thanks to fable and
mythos that it can be cut off at a
moment's notice and it needs an open
weight stack and I I think Alex Karp is
trying to to channel all of that animous
>> and so and I want to hit I want to hit
this point first which is if in fact you
know the the dominant players of open AI
and anthropic are uh if you're at risk
of losing your [clears throat]
proprietary data to them uh without even
knowing it uh then versus being able to
operate on an openweight model on your
own uh hardware which
>> that can't be shut off
>> that can't be shut off uh It is a future
that we need to consider is very real.
And so the question is where are the
openw weight large language models here
in the US? We've got Neotron coming
online. Uh we've got Google. What
happened to Meta? I mean Meta was
supposed to be the openweight player in
this field where I mean I I'm assuming
that Zuckerberg is working on that in
background mode and will come out as you
know that's his that's where I would be
playing if I were him. I'm going to call
it the dominant US player in openwave
models, but we'll see. It fell behind. I
mean, most of I I know many people who
were involved with Llama 4 who are no
longer with Meta, put it that way. And
Llama 5, whatever it's ultimately
branded, whether it gets branded as
Spark, uh, or something similar, may or
may not have GPT5 or Fable 5 level
capabilities. I don't know, TBD. But I I
I suspect just based on public
reporting, Meta which was in the race.
Hopefully Google stays in the race. XAI
may or may not visav Grock Cursor stay
in the race. There is totally I think a
gap for frontier openweight models
coming from Western institutions
including from Nvidia which has every
incentive to to produce frontier level
capabilities. It's just expensive and
hard at the moment.
>> And we're also getting full stack right.
So Nvidia coming in as a full stack
player um you know basically providing
the chips and the models um maybe you
know in through partnerships
applications
>> well Nvidia will be happy to commoditize
everything at the software layer if it
means selling more GPUs. Yeah, keep in
>> mind, you know, every single Magnum
Mobster company is designing its own
chips except for Anthropic now.
>> And so Nvidia's, you know, strangle hold
on 80% gross margins is not forever. And
so if Nvidia can create an open- source
model and it gets distributed through
Palunteer and a few other people that
puts competitive pressure back on
Anthropic because the way things are
trending right now, every dollar in AI
is flowing through Anthropic at
massively increasing margins.
>> Wait, I've got a couple of things I want
to say about this.
>> Yeah, sure. Okay. So, Karp's core
argument is that enterprises should
freak out that they're that paying for
tokens may also mean they're they're
releasing and leaking their operational
knowledge, right? The the like
>> Yeah. Your data exhaust is now the new
oil and maybe it's even the new national
security per. So, he's freaking
everybody out on that for reasonably
selfish reasons, etc. If you rent
intelligence um and give away your if
you rent intelligence but you lose your
context right you may be funding your
own replacement that's the freak out I
think the bigger question if you go one
level deeper is who owns the learning
loop is it the model provider is it the
enterprise is it the state or is it the
customer right and this is the key thing
enterprises are going to need to own
their learning loop and whatever it
takes to own that and I think we're
going to end up with onrem models as
you've mentioned Peter
running on with
personal data and custom data and that's
where the learning loop will go the
biggest
>> well on on prem everything will be in
space so on prem is an interesting word
>> well private clouds call it
>> yeah private
>> well the organizational singularity has
to migrate to orbit obviously [laughter]
>> it will have to migrate to I
>> I agree it'll it's a it's a race right
now between everything going to
anthropic open AI or what we're calling
onrem which is in space but private
cloud clouds but inspected
some other way. Right. Right now,
Enthropic has agreed to inspect
everything for the government. Uh and so
if you go private cloud then some other
inspection mechanism has to come into
existence which Palunteer will probably
contribute to. Everybody welcome
[snorts] to the health section of
Moonshots brought to you by Fountain
Life. You know AI is impacting every
aspect of our lives. How we teach our
kids, how we do our business. But one of
the most important things that AI can
deliver to us is health. And one of the
things I think about when, you know,
shooting for 100, 120 is, am I going to
have the cognitive health to be able to
think clearly and keep my wits about me
for the next 50 years? I'm joined here
today by Dr. Don Musalem, the chief
medical officer of Fountain Life and a
member of my Fountain Life medical team.
Don, a pleasure. So, Don, talk to me
about brain health.
>> Brain health, you know, you're right.
This is the number one concern people
coming into Fountain Life have is will I
remember the name of my child in the
face of my loved one. 45% of dementia
cases are entirely preventable with
lifestyle. And what was really
intriguing to me, Peter, is that a
quarter of our members had advanced
brain age. But over 13 months of us
really helping them live healthier
lifestyles, eating healthier, moving
their body regularly, and optimizing
sleep. People overlook that so often,
but that sleep optimization is critical
for our brain health. What we showed is
that we were able to improve the brain
age in 46% of those individuals. That's
a powerful number.
>> That's amazing. You know, one of the
things I love about Fountain is we're
constantly searching the world for the
most advanced therapeutics and bringing
them to our members. So, for me, all of
you, I hope that you appreciate the fact
that you can become the CEO of your own
health. you can make sure that you've
got the cognitive clarity for the next
50 years. Come and check it out.
fountainlife.com/pater
to learn more and become the CEO of your
health. Now, back to the episode. So,
Dave, let's jump into the story that we
were talking about back and forth. Uh AI
is now designing better AI chips and
training data is the catch 22. So, our
final story uh predicts a massive
acceleration of the innermost loop i.e.
uh AWG's catchphrase and
>> shock shocked to see recursive
self-improvement in this era of
recursive self-improvement.
>> Yes. Amazing
>> of AI designing chips that power AI. So,
here's the background. Uh designing
radio frequency circuits, RF guts are,
you know, part of every wireless device
and they've often been called a dark
art. In other words, [clears throat] it
takes humans weeks of painstaking trials
to design these RF circuits and these
chips. Last week, researchers at
Princeton working with IIT Madras uh
decided to hand that job to a machine.
And here's the clever part. It's not one
AI, but two working together. First,
they trained a convol convolutional
neural net, the same kind of model built
for image recognition to predict the
physics. Feed any shape, and it tells
you the EM fields, how the EM fields
will behave without ever taking the slow
route of solving Maxwell's equations. uh
what used to take traditional solvers uh
minutes to hours now takes milliseconds.
Uh then they send an AI loop over that a
thousand times, tens of thousands of
times, inventing wild, non-intuitive
circuits, shapes that no human would
ever create. The result are designs that
took weeks now being finished in
minutes. But here's the catch and the
tease. The AIS require training data and
all that training data is locked up in
yes you got it the magnumopsta uh
companies out there. So uh the question
is if this training data can be unlocked
can we see an intelligence explosion in
the design of AI chips which is the
inner innermost loop. So Dave what's
your thoughts on this one? Oh, so many
thoughts. But you know, uh, just to
clarify one part of that, the the
convolutional neural net is effectively
acting like a simulator. And any place
you can build a simulator, the AI can
have a field day because it can check
its own work and it can it can work for
weeks or months uh, improving itself if
the simulator is accurate. And so when
it comes to
>> unintentional pun, I assume a field day.
>> Oh.
>> Oh, inevitable. Sorry. Sorry.
>> Absolutely unintentional. [laughter]
Extremely. Uh so um so the the chip area
you know is is going to be massively
impactful for the recursive
self-improvement of AI and it's an open
question right now whether that data is
truly locked inside Nvidia and a couple
of other companies or whether the
simulators are good enough to allow you
to just generate a circuit see if it
would have worked to generate the next
see if it would have worked. So those
are in a foot race right now. But
regardless, it's incredible to me that
the magnumoba, you got 11 companies in
Magna Mobsta that are completely
dominant in the global market cap. Every
single one of them designing its own AI
chips except for Anthropic. Anthropic is
the one hold.
>> Anthropic just announced they they did
they just reported in the past few days
I think they're partnering with Samsung
on their own inference accelerators.
>> All right. All right. Well, so this this
is a real moment in time in in history
because you if you look at the biggest
companies in the world historically,
you'd have like an Exxon Mobile, an IBM,
a GE, all doing different things. Here
we have the 11 biggest in the world
doing the exact same thing. That's how
big a deal this race to AI, you know,
innermost loop, which includes the
chips, how how big a deal that is. So
it's it's, you know, it's a moment in
history that's pretty unprecedented. So
this verticalization,
do you expect it to continue and in
intensify?
>> I would be shocked if the inference time
custom chips aren't at least 100x and
maybe 10,000x
the performance that we're currently
seeing which will translate directly
into IQ.
I mean the rate of acceleration from
here, this is why it's clearly going to
be a hard takeoff. The rate of
acceleration will be unbelievable. Now,
keep in mind those chips are not
deployed yet. So, we haven't seen the
effect of that, but it'll it'll come
soon. And uh and when it hits, they're
also likely to consume less power, uh be
cheaper and easier to manufacture, so
more will come out of the limited fabs
that we've got, it's going to be a very
fast takeoff after that.
>> Talk to building better tools.
>> And have you looked at the design of
these RFICs, the RF integrated circuits?
They don't look human. They don't look
designed and I they they look more like
QR codes than anything else. And I I
think this is instructive as to what AI
super optimized designs of the future
are going to look like. That we're
familiar right now. If you look around
you on on a street in in a normal town
in America, you see a bunch of things.
You see cars, you see houses, you see
streets. These are all manifestly
human-designed artifacts.
>> As we start to
>> Yeah. uh they they're relatively simple.
They're easy to parse as you say Peter
they often follow some sort of rectal
linear style form. Now on the other hand
split screen look at super optimized
designs from the AI. They'll tend to
look more quote unquote organic. They'll
be noisier. They'll be more information
dense, harder to interpret
mechanistically.
>> Yeah. And I think that that's what there
there's this landscape out there for any
given physical system that you want to
to have do something useful for you
where there's a subset and the ven
diagram of of design space that's human
understandable and human designable but
then there's this dark matter outside of
that inner circle that's AI optimizable
and AI interpretable. And we're going to
discover over and over again starting
maybe with RF antennas and RFIC's in
this case that the AI optimized designs
look alien and biological and look
nothing like human designs.
>> That's so true. It's it's really worth
looking at the pictures actually to to
get a sense. But you know a lot of the
way human engineering works is in layers
of of abstraction otherwise it just
boggles your mind. And when you look at
chip design, you know, the modules are
pre-esigned, you know, for a memory
module, an interconnect module,
whatever. And then you drag and drop
them. So they it looks like a work of
art in the end. And then you look at
what the AI does and it looks like a
Borg spaceship, you know, like wow. But
the same is true with the microode. You
know, Alex, he sent me that paper on AI
writing kernels to run on these chips.
>> And the microode also is virtually
impossible to read,
>> but it's super efficient and you can't
deny that it works. and you run it and
it just it's it's clearly right, but
it's not built modularly and easy to
understand. And so so it also is this
layer of very tangled code on this layer
of very tangled chip design, but it's so
fast and so efficient that you just got
to do it.
>> The other thing I I thought was
interesting in this uh Princeton E paper
is they don't call it this, but I would
caricature it as an interpretability
tax. They added a knob that enabled you
to or the designer of these RFIC's to
tune up or tune down the level of
interpretability. So if you wanted a
less efficient design that was more
human interpretable, you would sort of
lower the the spatial resolution of
these AI designs, you wanted something
that's less interpretable but more
efficient, you could turn the knob up.
And I I think the notion of an
interpretability tax is something that
we're likely to see over and over again
in AI.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. You also see a lot of Claude
explaining things to you,
>> manplaining things to you. Basically,
[laughter]
>> Claude explaining
>> Claude explaining. Yeah. It's like,
look, I know you can't really understand
what I'm saying here. So, let me give
you like a highle overview that you'll
grasp and you're like, "Okay, that's
fine. As long as it works."
>> So, the question on this the question on
this article is who owns the end product
here? Is it the human or is it the AI?
Which is going to lead us to our next
story, gentlemen.
Uh this is out of Japan. It's the future
of IP ownership in an AI economy. Uh
Japan's Supreme Court has ruled that AI
cannot be listed as an inventor on a
patent application. The case is based on
a patent filing by US engineer Stefan
Thaylor who claimed an AI is the
inventor of technology related to food
containers and other products. Japan's
patent office rejected the application
and asked the h asked for a human
inventor. Theor refused. The case moved
to the Tokyo District Court, the
Intellectual Property High Court, and
now Japan Supreme Court, which upheld
the view that inventors under current
Japanese patent law must be natural
persons. The court's message is
important. They say, "Hey, basically,
you know, uh judges are not going to
rewrite the patent system on the fly. If
society wants AI generated inventors, uh
to receive protection, uh then you need
to create a new framework." So, two
fundamental questions. First, who owns
an idea when the idea emerges from a
model trained on the world prompted by a
human? And second, will any nation
rewrite their IP laws first to avoid the
need for meat puppets? So, Alex, uh, you
and I have talked about the notion that
out of the current, uh, AGI and ASI
ascendancy, we're going to see trillions
of dollars of of wealth created in
breakthroughs fundamental to math,
science, physics, biology, and material
sciences. And the question is, who's
going to own them? Your thoughts, Alex?
President Javier Mle, if you're
listening to this podcast, and you want
Argentina to take a globally preeminent
position from the perspective of
non-human AI corporations being able to
create their own IP and their own
patents. I I think Japan just opened up
a new market opportunity for for
Argentina. I I think it's probably worth
noting in the story that the underlying
patent applications date to before Chat
GPT. They they were originally filed in
2020. So this is this is this has been
brewing for some time and with less
sophisticated AI than what one might
otherwise suspect. It's probably also
worth noting that Japan's Supreme Court
didn't indefinitely rule out the
possibility of AI inventors on patents.
They were merely saying that the
existing statutes don't contemplate
non-natural persons. It's probably also
worth pointing out that to my
understanding of of international patent
law, it it is relatively standard to
only consider natural persons as
inventors. For example, again, to to my
lay understanding, US corporations
aren't able to be inventors for patents.
They're able to be assigned patents, but
they can't be the inventors of patents.
So there is a bit of precedental bias
towards so-called natural persons here
as patent inventors and away from
non-natural persons. However, however,
however, this is obviously the sort of
precedent that if and when some form of
AI personhood is ultimately recognized,
even if it's a partial economic or some
sort of social personhood. I I think
this is the sort of precedent that's
just waiting to be overturned.
>> Yeah, I think this topic is extremely
important, too. You guys had, you know,
Peter, you and Alex had a really lively
debate on this. Uh I think it was two
podcasts ago, but you know, historically
in the venture world, and the investing
world, the the mantra has always been if
you're relying on a patent, you're
doomed.
>> Yeah.
>> Like your business needs to needs to
survive and grow and thrive. The patents
get granted many years later. They're
very hard to enforce. blah blah blah
blah blah
>> need to be reinforced. Yes,
>> I think going forward intellectual
property is going to be an exponentially
growing important category of endeavor
and that um the US will end up enforcing
intellectual property rights globally
for things invented in America.
>> Can you imagine the speed of patent
applications as AI unleash become
allowed and unleash their creativity on
all these fields? Well, also, uh, you
know, one of our companies constructs
writes the patent. Like, you know,
historically, one of the biggest
barriers to getting your patent is
>> the $100,000 legal bill to get it
drafted over the course of months and
that the torture of that process.
>> Now, there are multiple startups that
just do it. You know, here's the idea,
AI, write it up and
>> and they have a huge corpus of data to
pull from of, you know, the the most
successful patents out there. Well, you
know, amazingly enough, they also
predict the inspector that you're likely
to get and then look at their past
behavior and try and predict what the
inspector will do with different
terminology. Exactly. So much better
than a human lawyer at writing these
applications.
>> So that the rate of applications will go
through the roof
>> and so then the you know the patent
office is going to have to respond by
reading them with AI and that's going to
lead to this whole intellectual property
explosion. So then the question question
is enforcement. um is the US going to
get out in the world and enforce and I
think they'll easily be able to do it
with trade law. You know, the government
the military doesn't have to go into
every country to say, "Hey, you're
stealing all our IP." Trump has proven
that with tariffs alone, you can compel
virtually any behavior globally because
the US economy is just that strong and
accelerating. So assuming that trend
continues then intellectual property
rights will be enforced globally and
then this this whole area will become
really important to to keep uh following
and talking about.
>> I also think the same tools of super
intelligence maybe tools is an
overstatement are ultimately going to be
available to every aspect of IP. So the
invention stage super intelligence, the
application stage and the the patent
drafting stage super intelligence. the
filing and uh say overall regulatory
processes at the patent office or
otherwise of recognizing and granting
say patent state patent status super
intelligence litigation super
intelligence litigation defense super
intelligence the court systems that are
overseeing and mediating the defense
super intelligence
>> working around your patent super
intelligence
>> yeah exactly this I think the whole
system is completely broken. But go back
to the crisper patent, right? Within
within a few months, people had found
eight or nine different mechanisms to
deliver the same thing. After years of
fighting over the the one patent, they
got ratted around very quickly. That's
just going to happen at such an
accelerated pace with super
intelligence, whatever we want to define
it as, that you're going to end up in
this whole mess. The whole system is
essentially irrelevant going forward. I
>> I'll I'll take a different position on
this. I don't think the system is
irrelevant. I I simply think the the
routing around sem that you refer to in
the in the instance of crisper this
would have happened on some time scale
anyway but with modern tooling and
modern technologies the natural process
can happen on a faster time scale and
the I would say that the key time scale
here is so order of magnitude patent I
mean there are lots of ways it could be
extended or or otherwise uh changed but
call it like a 15-year time scale for a
patent what happens when the time scale
thanks to super int intelligence for
identifying routarounds, prior art,
defenses, offenses, compliments becomes
so much faster than a characteristic
15-year time scale that it's the time
scale of patent protection that's in
some sense lossing out. It's not that
the regime itself is bad or that patent
defensibility is dead or anything. It's
just that innovation is happening so
quickly relative to the originally I I
think it's a statutory statutoily set
time scale of patents that there's
pressure to change the time scale.
>> So this is the canary in the coal mine.
This is going to hit us on so many
different legal fronts in our current
structure. Right? because the entire
legal structure of of every nation has
been built on human time scales and and
and
uh the the speed at which humans can
process information. Uh and it's all
going to break and all going to be
reinvented.
>> Look, the simplest example is we have a
representative democracy. Yes.
>> Where Congress meets occasionally
because a couple hundred years ago the
fastest that information could travel
was the speed of a horse. Yeah, I have
to give people time to ride across the
country and say here's what my people
are saying
>> and the same way occasionally
>> innovation innovation will only occur at
the edge which is when you start a new
country and you redesign it from scratch
right so this is where we're you know
there's going to be this is I always
talk about we're going to start new
countries in cyerspace we're going to
start new countries outside of the
earth's uh you know orbital
>> back to the accelerondo plots
>> yeah yeah
future big big fan for what it's worth
of starting new countries in outer
space. The outer space treaty, it
doesn't look necessarily super favorably
on starting denovo countries in outer
space, but I I think it's going to
happen.
>> Have you read the moon is a harsh
mistress? Leave us alone.
>> Classic.
>> We will land rocks on you if if you
don't agree.
>> Moon is the ultimate high ground.
>> The ultimate high ground.
>> Rods from
>> I wish you a good evening. Um thank you
for a great conversation today. Uh
everybody uh I hope you en enjoyed this
wide ranging conversation from
consciousness to patent IP law. Dave
buddy be well sem
>> I have a plug in two weeks I'm I'm two
weeks I'm having my next meaning of life
session July 21st 7 p.m. online we'll
put the links below
>> but uh
>> how long did it go last time?
>> Uh last time was 6 and 1/2 hours and we
had more than 3/4 of the people still
there at 6 and 1/2 hours. I had to call
it.
>> Oh my god.
>> So, we'll we'll do it again and see if
we can make it a little more efficient.
>> Fantastic. Alex, any any breaking news
in your world?
>> Don't take off the takeoff. It's now a
song.
>> I I I love your neogisms. Everybody
check out Alex's innermost loop
substack. Uh it's uh it's a beautiful
thing to wake up to the morning. Uh and
I've got my Substack uh on there as
well. We'll put links in the show notes
here. Uh Dave, are you publishing yet?
>> Go to db2.ai. Keep your eyes open.
>> All right. Fantastic.
>> Oh, you know what I am doing?
>> What are you doing?
>> I'm adding I'm doing uh AMA sessions for
some of the comments in a separate video
on our YouTube channel because it's too
it's too difficult to try and answer all
these questions.
>> All right, gentlemen. I wish you a good
night or good morning depending on what
part of the planet you're in.
[music]